He went back to the agency and told them
"Destroy all the documents." And I said,
half jokingly, "So, where are the
aliens?"
And he laughed and he said, "That is"
and many, many nights after that
was just a man's voice
saying
eight
three
six. And then somebody at the CIA said,
"We've got to smuggle this into the
Soviet Union. How do you do that?"
Well, we could do it by You're in this
meeting and a determination is made that
yes, we're going to do this. We're going
to call it MK Ultra. She said, "It's all
about weapon sales."
All of these meetings. We found
Nordine's head on the roof of the next
door neighbor's house. I hate coming off
as a conspiracy theorist, but and I
believe very strongly that the Israelis
knew exactly what was going [music] to
happen, exactly when it was going to
happen. We created chaos in Iraq and
chaos in Syria and chaos in Libya
[music] and now chaos in Iran. This
isn't anything that's new. It's been
going on for more than a century. I was
with him for the first 56 consecutive
hours of his captivity.
I tied him to the hospital bed. He had
surgery. Oh my god, I could talk about
this for the next 2 hours.
All right, welcome to Jay's Analysis,
guys. Thank you for joining me today. We
have an esteemed guest, somebody that I
consider a true patriot and a hero.
We have with us John Kiriakou. You've
probably seen him all over the podcast
blowing up everywhere in the last few
months. He is a former essential
intelligence agency officer,
whistleblower, journalist, author, and
now podcaster. And he joins me today to
talk about how the world really works,
the myths and realities of espionage.
We're going to talk about history. We're
going to talk about current topics.
John, how are you?
I'm well, thanks, Jay. How are you?
Good. We had a a good time talking
before, and so I thought, man, this guy
really knows his stuff. I've listened to
I don't know how many hours of you in
the last
in the last several months, and it's so
weird because when you listen to
somebody over and over and over on the
internet, you start to feel like oh,
yeah, I know that guy, but you don't
actually know that guy. So, um
there is a sort of a familiarity, and of
course we do have a lot of things in
common.
Let's start it off with some notes that
I jotted down after listening to a lot
of the recent interviews that you've
done. Of course, guys, you did just
appear on Tucker, and I think that went
up yesterday or the night before. Yeah,
and so be sure and check that out.
John's channel is of course linked, and
he does his channel Deep Focus, and
let's start with something that's a
little spicy from the outset. I hear a
lot of former CIA people, pro-CIA
people, present CIA people, they they do
a sort of apologetic, which I
understand,
but they argue that the West and the CIA
never really engaged in sexual espionage
or that kind of operation because of the
legalities that it would interfere with
and the the the the rights that people
have. But, we hear all kinds of stories
as well about Operation Midnight Climax,
where this is kind of farmed out to, you
know, the organized crime and this kind
of stuff, and we hear about Epstein and
the possible connections with various
intelligence agencies throughout the
world. So, is it a situation where it's
not on the books, but it's done kind of
on the side? Can you speak to that?
Oh, yeah, I can speak to it. Um
the CIA, since its inception, has been
involved in sexual operations, sexual
espionage. Certainly, sex was was a
well-documented component of MKUltra,
which lasted from about 1952
to 1975.
People are going to jump on my head for
saying it ended in 1975. It ended in
1975.
Certainly, there are other operations
that could be considered successors to
MKUltra, but MKUltra ended in '75. You
talked about Operation Midnight Climax,
that's one of the more famous ones. It's
one of those operations that we talk
about today in 2026, and you just have
to shake your head and and ask
semi-rhetorically, "What in the world
were they thinking?"
But yeah, I mean sex was used routinely
well into the late '70s, the early '80s.
One of the very first questions, Jay,
that I asked when I joined not not the
CIA, but when I joined operations, which
was about halfway through my CIA career,
was about the use of honey pots, right?
because when you're when you're learning
counterintelligence,
you learn how the Russians use honey
pots, the Israelis use honey pots. Well,
what about us?
And
one of my instructors, who became my
mentor, quite a famous officer, Gus
Avrakotos, he was played by Philip
Seymour Hoffman in the film Charlie
Wilson's War. Gus told me, "We used sex
all the time until Ronald Reagan became
president." And and not we didn't stop
because Ronald Reagan became president,
but roughly that period, only because it
just didn't work after a while. If you
really want somebody to be a source for
you and to commit espionage for you over
the course of, you know, years,
that relationship has to be built on a
foundation of trust, not one of
coercion.
And so, you know, if you go up to
somebody and say, "Listen, we set you up
with a prostitute the other night and
you didn't know, but we had the room
wired for video and audio, and we have
these pictures of you and videos, and
we're going to release them to your
wife, or we're going to release them to
your government unless you work for us."
That's not how you build trust. That's
not how you build a long-term
relationship. And then he told me a
story, it very well could be apocryphal,
but I've I've always believed it. And
that was before the Iranian Revolution,
there was an Ayatollah that we wanted to
recruit and so we sent a prostitute to
kind of bump him and lure him into um
into a hotel and he had sex with her and
we took pictures and video and then laid
it out in front of him and said, "We've
got you."
And he laughed. And he said, "I'll take
that in an 8 by 10 and give me two 5 by
7s of this one." And he's like, "What's
wrong with you guys?
Seriously, like in the movies you're
going to try to threaten me? Get out of
here."
And it was around that operation that a
decision was made that this just isn't
working. If the Israelis and the
Russians think it works for them, that's
fine for them, but we just stopped doing
it.
Well, that's interesting because, you
know, when when we look into Epstein and
then the files and the emails and all
these dumps that that recently came out,
you know, there was quite a bit. I don't
know if you had ever any time to read
like Whitney Webb's book. I thought it
was
>> Oh, yeah, Whitney Webb is terrific.
Whitney's book was great and I think she
demonstrates, you know, that this is
sort of a a copy-paste operation going
back to Robert Maxwell and then whoever
perhaps recruited Robert Maxwell be the
Rothschilds or whoever into doing it and
and taught him the ropes. It seems like
that situation was relying very heavily
on compromise. Many of the the details
in the emails that are still somewhat
ambiguous and hard to figure out, they
seem to point in that direction.
I remember somebody saying
maybe it was Andrew Bustamante on a
video or something. But somebody was
saying something like "Well, once you do
this, you kind of
you can never do anything with them
again because they're up forever we're
to hate you. So you're not, like you
said, building trust. It kind of kind of
maybe as a last resort. Is that why they
would rely on something like that for,
you know, so many politicians and
members of Congress? Is it Is it a last
resort or is it a first resort for some
some countries?
You know, I can give you an educated
guess and I'm going to say that it's
probably a first resort for a lot of
countries. It's unusual for me to agree
with something that Andrew Bustamante
has to say, but he I think he's right
about that. And then coming back to
something that you said just a moment
ago,
we have to also consider the use of
cutouts.
So, that the chance of blowback
is lessened. And what I mean by that is
why would you set someone up in a
compromising sexual position and risk
it going bad and then having that
blowback on you when you can have
a cutout do it.
You can have Jeffrey Epstein do it. You
can have a foreign intelligence service
do it for you or
an organized criminal gang or something
that doesn't point back to the CIA. You
know, look at it this way, too.
We learned so much from this latest
tranche of the Epstein documents, so
much. And there are still three to three
and a half million pages that the
president is now saying will not be
released, apparently because they would
embarrass friends of his. But
we now know that Jeffrey Epstein
apparently
was
an access agent for the Israelis, but
that he had also volunteered
to work for the CIA, to work for the
FBI, to work for the British MI5 and the
British MI6 and the Germans and that he
had tried repeatedly to get a private
one-on-one meeting with Vladimir Putin.
He couldn't quite get the meeting, but
the Russians offered a meeting with
Putin and two security officials, which
Epstein had turned down. So, I think
that the answer to your question is most
likely yes.
Uh that this is going on, that it always
has gone on, and if it wasn't
a direct
CIA operation to use sex to to gather
information,
it was a CIA operation to use a cutout
to use sex to get information.
Yeah.
>> Yeah, I think often times people think
of this is something that's only a
government agency as if it couldn't be
Yeah, as if it couldn't be farmed out to
organized crime. You know, Exactly. You
you know, you watch The Godfather and
the second Godfather, you know, they
they get the politician Yeah.
>> the the Corleone's whorehouses. So,
so they got their you know, they got the
blackmail that they needed in that
situation. So, yeah, I think that's a
great point is you know, the use of
cutouts and I don't mean to go too much
into Hollywood and movies. My wife and I
were watching Peaky
Grinders. That's a joke, but making fun
of a guy that Peaky Blinders.
There was a situation where you know,
the British government with SIS at that
time, I guess, was working with
you know, Cillian Murphy's or Irish
criminal gang, and together they're
having to combat the IRA and the
communists, and they're using the
organized crime some in some cases to to
do a hit.
And I remember reading in some of the
books on Operation Underworld and some
of the stories of you know, the Genovese
crime syndicate after World War I. Yes.
The US intelligence apparatus at that
time was even kind of making links with
with organized crime. How significant
and real do you believe those links were
to the underground world of organized
crime from the American intelligence
apparatus over the the decades of the
20th century? Is it over Is it
exaggerated? Is that something that is
very important? Strong. And with the
advent of the Freedom of Information Act
and mandatory declassification laws, we
now have more details about some of
these relationships. As you correctly
pointed out, the FBI worked very closely
with the Genovese family to secure the
Port of Brooklyn and the Port of Newark
during the Second World War. We know how
many different times the CIA worked with
the Santo Trafficante family in Tampa to
try to assassinate Fidel Castro.
There are other examples, too. I have to
be careful here. Well, you know, an
obvious one from the 1980s
is when the CIA was working with
the Pablo Escobar cartel to target
communist separatists in Colombia in the
jungle. DEA was doing one thing, CIA's
doing exactly the opposite thing and
nobody saw the irony in that. There's a
famous case with a mob hitman, I think
he was a Colombo, named Greg Scarpa,
where Scarpa was recruited by the FBI to
go to Mississippi to find these three
freedom writers, Chapman, Chaney, I
forget the third one's name, who had
been murdered by the Ku Klux Klan. And
Scarpa actually kidnapped a clansman and
shot him in the knees to force him to
tell them where the bodies were and
then, like magic, the FBI discovers the
bodies in an earthen dam outside of
town. So, yeah, you go through the
entire history really of the FBI and the
history of the CIA and there are lots of
examples where they worked very closely
with organized crime.
Yeah, and that actually is a great
transition to the next topic I wanted to
ask you about and that's Operation
Gladio because Gladio is another example
of a very close connection between
Western intelligence agencies and
organized crime, particularly Sicilian
mafia,
and what we know is is the P2 Lodge, or
the Propaganda Due A Lodge in Italy. And
this was a post-World War II sort of,
oddly enough, fascist-tending
a series of lodges that were able to be
sources for recruitment, according to
the public journalistic material that we
have, on the part of the CIA and other
outfits to sort of again recruit from
also organized crime. We have the
character Michele Sindona, and we have
the character Licio Gelli.
And that ties into secret societies as
well as Masonic networks, things like
that. Is Gladio a huge component of that
post-World War II alliance with the
Vatican and Vatican bank structure, or
is this exaggerated?
I always believed that what we've
learned publicly, let me preface this by
saying everything I learned about
Operation Gladio, I learned after I left
the CIA. It was in 1990 that the Italian
Prime Minister, and I think it was
Andreotti at the time, went public when
speaking to Parliament about Operation
Gladio. For your viewers who don't know
what Gladio is, it was an operation
hatched by the CIA, MI6, the Vatican,
and NATO
to
leave
essentially sleeper agents behind
right at the end of World War II
and in the couple of years after, just
in case of a Soviet invasion, so that
there would be an intelligence structure
in place that could help the Western
services confront the Soviets.
You know, in retrospect, looking at it
in 2026, it seems kind of quaint,
you know, the thing of an interesting
movie that might, you know, get
nominated for an Academy Award or two.
But back then it was deadly serious.
Deadly serious. We really believed the
Soviets were going to invade Western
Europe. We really believed it. And so
people were scrambling to create an
intelligence infrastructure. Keep in
mind, too,
that the CIA and NATO weren't created
until 1947. So there was this period of
of about a year and a half from '45 to
early '47 where
we were just winging it. MI6 was sort of
the preeminent intelligence service in
the Western world, with the KGB being
the preeminent service in the Eastern
world. And President Truman's advisers
were saying, "Listen, we need to be
prepared for a Soviet invasion of
Western Europe." And so
Truman asked the British
to send MI6 officers to New York
to sit with Americans and to help us
create what he called a central
intelligence agency. A place where all
foreign intelligence could be collected
and analyzed.
You know, just as a kind of a funny
aside, all of this ended up happening as
part of what's called the National
Security Act of 1947. J. Edgar Hoover,
the the long, long time director of the
FBI, he was the head of the FBI for 40
what? 48 years?
He was strongly opposed to the creation
of a CIA and an NSC. The National
Security Council was also created in
that same National Security Act of 1947.
So he was going around Capitol Hill
asking members of Congress to vote
against it. And this is exactly the
opposite of what President Truman
wanted. Truman got wind that
Hoover was working against passage of
the bill. And so he called Hoover in
and told Hoover, "You've got this all
wrong.
This central intelligence agency, it's
going to be a component of the FBI.
So you'll be head of the FBI and of the
CIA."
And he said, "Oh." And he lifted his
objection. It was a lie, of course.
There was never any intention for the
CIA to be a division of the FBI.
And Hoover never forgave Truman for
lying to him. But we were scrambling in
and early 1947, finally these MI6
officers came to New York.
They were met by
Bill Donovan and Prescott Bush and a
handful of other swells from, you know,
Wall Street and the OSS days. And with
some, you know, pads of paper, they came
up with a centralized intelligence
service that we called the CIA.
Yeah, it's a fascinating history. I
remember several texts that discuss the
extreme influence, I guess you could
say, from British intelligence on how to
structure it, how to set it up. Uh
several early figures were very well
trained by the British, like Frank
Wisner. Yeah, he's a legend.
>> student. Yeah, a massive student of
British counterintelligence. But in
terms of like, going back to Gladio real
quick, a lot of writers conceive of this
as a template, something that is not
just about, you know, setting up
networks within Europe that would stave
off a Soviet NKVD-style
takeover, but also perhaps train terror
cells that could be activated later on.
Now, we know that perhaps Gladio
probably ended, but maybe other types of
operations or templates that some
authors, I think Doug Valentine and
others, connect
>> Yeah. Yeah, they connect these types of
operations to the template of
Iran-Contra training, you know, the
right-wing death squads there. And also
ISIS-Al-Qaeda-type training Yeah. that
you would get under Brzezinski and
Carter and Gates in the late '70s, early
'80s for the Soviet situation. Do you
think that's accurate? Is that
exaggerated? Is it a template that's
used? One last point, I remember reading
Miles Copeland's book, Game of Nations,
and he was discussing that
in his time in Egypt and in Syria, when
he was a consultant to the governments
there. Obviously, he says I was working
for the CIA. He says,
"We would use terrorists all the time."
He says, "They're they're great patsies
and dupes." I'm not saying that the CIA
runs every terror operation, but he says
it's a very useful tool in the toolkit.
Is that accurate? Is this exaggerated as
well? Is it a template, a way to
structure Iran-Contra, ISIS, Gladio?
>> Oh, yeah. No, it's not exaggerated. And
I would actually take issue with his
statement that they're dupes. They're
not dupes. They're partners.
They're compensated handsomely.
You bank a favor that way. Well, I I
think he's saying the person who goes in
and actually blows himself up is the
dupe, but Oh, totally. But maybe the
handlers are are not dupes. No, no. I
I'm with you on that. Yes, I
misunderstood. Uh yeah, that that would
be the the dupe. I mean, even somebody
like me, that that was not really my
world at the CIA. I was strictly a
counterterrorism officer, but even I had
contact with organized crime overseas.
We didn't give each other the warm and
fuzzies, and we didn't invite each other
to dinner at each other's homes, or
introduce each other to our respective
wives, but we shook hands, and money
exchanged hands, and I got what I
wanted, and he got what he wanted, and
then we never saw each other again.
That's actually quite a common
event. There's risk, of course, because
you're dealing with people who, you
know, in some cases are stone-cold
killers.
And you need to trust them to a point
where they do what you're paying them to
do. The initial encounter is what's the
most dangerous, I think. I I have told
the story. I was dealing with a
with an organized crime figure overseas
in the Middle East, and there was a
French intelligence officer dealing with
him as well. And the French intelligence
officer one day was just found dead in a
ditch on the side of the road. And so,
we had to all meet, like, should I go to
the next meeting?
Are they going to kill me at the next
meeting? I don't know. I said I don't
think he's going to kill me. I think he
trusts me.
So, I go to the next meeting. It was
very tense. It turned out to be our last
meeting. And as I was walking out, he
says to me, "Oh, by the way." And I
turned and I looked at him and he said,
"Your French friend?
Very bad tradecraft."
And I wasn't really sure what to make of
that other than the fact that he was
admitting to me that he had killed the
French intelligence officer.
I don't know why he didn't try to kill
me.
But yeah, that kind of thing happens all
the time. It's It's a calculated risk
that you take. And you know, if the
gain, the potential gain is greater than
the potential risk, sure, you go forward
and you're very happy to meet with
criminals.
In regard to to terror, again, you being
expert
at the say on counterterrorism, dealing
with that, I think we in the world of
alternative media, we tend to think
immediately when you see when you hear
the word terror, you immediately think
false flag, you think staged, you think
engineered.
Certainly not every event is staged or
engineered, something like that. There
are organic believers in radical
ideologies. But we also have this
reality too of false flag events. If we
were to think back over the last say
century or last several decades,
how many instances would you guess or if
you had to do a percentage or some just
speculation, right? Like do you think
most
major terror events have a kind of
connection to a state or to some other
type of entity or or is it organic? Now,
that's a good That's a good question.
That's a tough question. You know what?
I'm going to have to say, "Oh, I'm going
to take a lot of [__] for this." I'm
going to have to say
that yes, I I most of them probably are
connected to a state in some way.
I hate coming off as a conspiracy
theorist, but when you dig down into
some of these operations,
I mean, look at 9/11.
I mean, 9/11 was carried out by
al-Qaeda. We know that. I'm 1,000%
confident 9/11 was carried out by
al-Qaeda. But, who was behind al-Qaeda?
Clearly, it was the Saudi government.
And I believe very strongly that the
Israelis knew exactly what was going to
happen, exactly when it was going to
happen, but it was to Israel's benefit
that the United States be attacked so
that the US would respond by killing 2
million Muslims over the next 20 years,
which is exactly what we did. We created
chaos in Iraq and chaos in Syria and
chaos in Libya and now chaos in Iran,
and that's to Israel's benefit. So, I
think in many, many cases,
yeah, there's a state behind it. And
I'll add one thing. I've talked about
this publicly many times, but the on the
night that we captured Abu Zubaydah in
March of 2002, we caught him in a in a
safe house in Faisalabad, Pakistan. One
of the things that we confiscated that
night was his diary.
And so,
I was with him for the first 56
consecutive hours of his captivity.
I tied him to the hospital bed. He had
surgery to treat three gunshot wounds.
We shot him we the Pakistanis shot him
while he was trying to escape that
night. And so, I was so sleepy I was
afraid I was going to fall asleep and he
was going to escape somehow. So, I tore
up a sheet, I tied him to the bed.
And I'm just sitting there at the foot
of the bed like this just kind of
staring at him for most of the 56 hours,
but one of the things that we
confiscated that night in the raid was
his diary.
And so, I started leafing through the
diary.
And it made my hair stand up. Most of it
was silly. Most of it was doodles. He
was an accomplished sketch artist.
Like, I would pay money for some of the
drawings that he did.
>> It would have been funny if the doodles
were like a like a high school teenage
girl's doodles. Right, right.
You know, with hearts over the letter I
and stuff like that. No. [laughter]
Um Terrorist Terrorist with a heart of
gold. Seriously. Misunderstood. He wrote
a lot of poetry.
Much of it which was quite good. He
wrote
letters to his younger self, which I
found fascinating. And this led to a
split between the CIA and the FBI, where
the FBI said he was a madman.
And the CIA said, "No, he's he's
extraordinarily intelligent." The CIA
turned out to be correct on that. He
would write these letters to himself,
like it was the the 27-year-old Abu
Zubaydah
or the or the 30-year-old Abu Zubaydah
writing to the 14-year-old Abu Zubaydah
saying, "Treat our mother with respect.
You were rude to her today. Don't
whistle at those girls. You're a Muslim
you're a Muslim you shouldn't whistle at
girls." You know, stuff like that.
But
what I also saw in the diary were three
cell phone numbers.
And they were to three members of the
Saudi royal family.
Why in God's name would
someone that we believed at the time was
the number three in Al-Qaeda. He wasn't
the number three, but he was a bad guy.
He had established and staffed
Al-Qaeda's two training camps in
southern Afghanistan, as well as
Al-Qaeda's safe house in Peshawar, the
house of martyrs. Why would he have the
personal cell phone numbers of three
Saudi princes?
And so we went to the Saudis and we
said, "Take care of this or we're going
to take care of it, and you're not going
to like the way we take care of it."
The next thing you know,
one of these princes dies on the
operating table during bariatric
surgery. They're all fat pigs. They're
all fat pigs.
The second prince is killed in a one-car
accident on the Riyadh to Jeddah
highway.
And the third prince goes camping in the
desert and dies of thirst.
So,
yeah.
That tells me that the last thing they
wanted was for the CIA to snatch these
guys
and to start interrogating them.
Which then, of course, led me to believe
that the Saudi government was involved
in 9/11.
Yeah, I mean,
so many things point that way. We even
had that as a 16 pages of Yeah, it turns
out the Saudi
>> pages. Yeah, the 20 Yeah, that the
Saudis did have a key role, turns out,
which many people theorized and
suspected. And that's our ally, right?
That's not a
>> friends in the Middle East. But they're
also one of the greatest funders of
terrorism.
>> But
it's a funder of terror,
Yeah. On the topic of
Saudi Arabia, I don't want to get too
far afield, but this made me think of
this. I remember reading recently that
Kissinger back in the 1970s had a very
important role
in restructuring
how the petrodollar would function in
the world. And that there was an
intentional shifting away from using US
oil or native oil here to put us in
reliance on foreign oil, like Saudis and
others,
to give us then an excuse to I thought
this was a really
cunning genius sort of conspiracy plot
here of a villain plot. So, now that now
we have an excuse for foreign policing
because we're tied to the oil that we
get from all these other countries. And
we heard recently with Trump, right,
that we've got to do all this for the
oil. We have to get the oil. We've got
the finish oil. There's oil we've got to
go get the oil.
>> oil. We got to take the oil. Well, don't
we have a lot of oil here? I thought
Trump ran on that, right? We've got so
much oil in the
>> on an ocean of oil.
>> an ocean of oil, but now we have to
police the world over oil. Is it a
plausible theory that Kissinger and I've
heard read via the Bilderberg meetings
at that time that they sort of planned
out the petrodollar as a excuse for
future world police?
I I think that's exactly what happened.
I think that's exactly what happened and
we're seeing still the effects today
50 years after
that policy was enacted. You know, I've
got a friend, former CIA friend,
who left the CIA and went into he's a
he's one of these genius um engineers.
And so he left the CIA and he went to
work for one of the big oil companies.
And he said something to me that was so
interesting. He said, "It's not
cost-effective to frack for oil if oil
is at $60 a barrel or lower."
Okay, if it's over 60, fracking is
cost-effective, it's profitable,
everybody's going to want to do it.
Okay, well,
oil is what? $110, $115
a barrel right now.
And we're fracking a little bit,
but what are we doing with the fracked
oil?
We're sending it to Japan.
We sell all that oil to Japan. So, why
would we export our own oil and import
Middle Eastern oil? Exactly.
>> Because that's exactly what we do. Well,
we do it to maintain that tie to the
Middle East.
And as much as I hate Henry Kissinger,
and I really do, the butcher of Cyprus,
the butcher of Chile, the butcher of
Cambodia, I hate Henry Kissinger.
He was telling us the truth
when he said that,
that this policy as
as
as calculating and cunning as it may
seem, it's it's a reality of American
foreign policy.
It really is.
Yeah, and and let's see, if if don't
mind, Jay, I No, feel free. to just to
speak a minute about Venezuela.
How does Venezuela fit in or not fit
into this? Venezuela is different. It's
separate. Venezuela's oil is is so
dirty.
It is so high in sulfur
that it can only be refined at specialty
refineries where they inject
tons of chemicals to try to purify it.
Even still, you can't purify it enough
to turn it into gasoline.
Right? And and these
these refineries exist
right now, for the most part, only in
South Florida. The Chinese built one
recently, the Indians built one, but for
the most part, the only refineries that
can handle this really dark heavy oil
are in Florida.
And the oil is used only for home
heating oil.
So, when we talk about oil and
international oil and OPEC, of which
Venezuela is a member, we have to keep
Venezuela sort of off to the side
because it's a different issue from a
foreign policy perspective.
Yeah, that's a great point, too, because
we don't think about these different
regions having very very different ways
that they fit into the global, you know,
system. But, I do want to ask you, too,
about briefly here because you had such
a There's so many places we could go.
You've had such an adventuresome life,
and I've listened to you many times tell
the stories of when you were stationed
in Greece and you were dealing with
the left. And the first thing that came
to my mind was, in in the case of these
leftist organizations, that one of which
I think tried to have you unalived,
shall we say? And feel free to rehearse
that story if you'd like because I think
this audience may not have heard it, but
the first thing that comes to my mind
when I hear this kind of stuff is, who
funds these things? Like, I've never
even heard of this left Greek this
organization that was radical left. And
then we always look to the money to see,
you know, who's funding this, who's
pushing this. Who would fund such a
thing and why? Would it be Soviet? You
know, I mean, the Cold War is kind of
coming to an end. Like, who would be
behind that? Oh my god. I could talk
about this for the next 2 hours.
I'm going to make it short. So, the
group you're talking about is called
Revolutionary Organization 17 November.
In October of 1975,
the CIA named a new station chief in
Athens. His name was Richard Welch.
Dick Welch was a Philhellene. He was a
lover of all things Greek. He had a
degree in the classics. He spoke ancient
Greek. He spoke modern Greek. He got a
master's degree in archaeology. This guy
just loved, loved, loved everything
Greece.
And he's named CIA station chief in
Athens. So, he arrives.
6 weeks later,
on December 23rd, 1975, he's invited to
the US ambassador's Christmas party.
He and his wife go to the ambassador's
Christmas party in their
chauffeur-driven car.
They have a good time, by all accounts.
And at the end of the party, they drive
back to their house.
In a very close-in very high-end suburb
of Athens called Psychiko. These are the
days before automatic door openers or
gate openers. So, the driver pulls up to
the gate and gets out of the car to open
the gate to drive into the property.
There is a car parked directly across
the street. There are three men and a
woman inside the car.
We never identified the woman.
Two of the men get out of the car and
one of them shouts in Greek, "Richard
Welch, get out of the car."
Dick gets out of the car and Mrs. Welch
gets out of the car. The driver runs for
his life.
One of the men says, "Richard Welch,
have been found guilty of crimes against
the Greek people and you've been
sentenced to death." And then shoots him
three times in the chest with a .45
caliber semi-automatic handgun that
became known as the Welch .45. They
killed 18 more people with that same gun
between 1975 and 2002.
They then got back in the car and drove
away.
The Greek police were so inept
that the killers had to call the cops a
week ago and say, "You idiots, the
getaway car we left abandoned at the
intersection of this street and that
street. Go get it."
In the meantime,
the killers wrote a manifesto. Now, this
became a theme. They would write a
manifesto at almost every attack over
the next 27 years.
But this manifesto
they
they sent to a sympathizer in Paris
and the sympathizer in Paris
hand-delivered it to the French
philosopher Jean-Paul Sartre.
Sartre read it and said, "What is this
craziness?" And he literally put it in a
desk drawer and forgot about it.
A year later,
the former chief of the Greek National
Police,
a man named Mallios,
he had been the chief of the Greek
National Police during the military
dictatorship and he was a he was a
deeply hated torturer.
He would leave his apartment every
single day at the same time
and buy a newspaper and go to the coffee
shop and drink coffee.
And this one day in April of 1976,
he
came out of his apartment. There There a
man and a woman there
making out.
And he told us later
on his deathbed
that he smiled when he saw them and he
thought to himself, "Young love in the
spring."
As soon as he walked past them
the man pulled out the Welch 45 and shot
him three times in the back.
He lived for 2 hours.
And the description he gave of the
shooter matched Mrs. Welch's description
of the shooter in her husband's
assassination.
They sent another manifesto to Jean-Paul
Sartre.
So, Sartre receives it. Actually, Sartre
didn't receive it. Bernard-Henri Lévy,
who is today France's most famous
philosopher and poet and was Sartre's
assistant at the time, he said, "Wait a
minute. We've received something like
this before."
And he found the original one
in the desk and then he sent them both
to Libération newspaper. It's the
leftist newspaper in Paris. They
published them.
That put 17 November on the map. 17
November was named after the date in
when there was a student uprising at the
Athens Polytechnic University where the
military dictatorship in its final death
rows opened fire with tanks on unarmed
students. And to hear the students tell
it, killed 500. To hear the fascist tell
it, they killed three dozen. We'll never
know. They destroyed most of the bodies.
But that put 17 November on the map. You
asked a very very important question.
Where did they get the money?
We just assumed in 1975 that these guys
were tied to the KGB.
But we had a long-standing agreement
with the KGB. You don't kill our guys
and we don't kill your guys.
We try to recruit each other's guys but
no killing.
And the the Russians came to us and they
said, "Listen, this was not us.
It just was not us." And then the
Bulgarians proactively came to us and
said, "We promise this was not us and we
can tell you it was not the Soviets."
We couldn't figure out who it was. So,
how did they get their money? How did
they self-finance?
They would rob banks and post offices.
Now, remember these were the days when
everything was done in cash, everything.
And they would just rob banks and post
offices in broad daylight.
And then they would raid police stations
in the middle of the night, grab the
handful of cops that were on duty, tie
them up, hold them hostage, steal all of
their weapons and all of their
ammunition. And just to add insult to
injury,
there is a large military museum in
Athens, right in the center of Athens.
The Greeks are very proud of it. And in
the 1980s,
somebody who was a member of 17 November
went into the military museum and
realized
that none of the weapons on display had
been deactivated.
They were all live weapons
on display, rocket launchers, machine
guns. So, they went one day, a group of
four terrorists went just as the museum
opened, took everybody hostage,
and then just took all of these live
weapons off the wall.
And then a couple of months later, they
raided a military weapons depot in
Larissa in central Greece
and stole all the ammunition needed for
the weapons that they stole from the
military museum.
So, they self-financed,
they self-armed,
and then there were specialty weapons
that they
somehow came into the possession of, and
that's where I came in.
I was able to identify analytically
a connection between 17 November and
Carlos the Jackal.
And if your viewers don't know who
Carlos the Jackal was, he was the Osama
bin Laden of the 1970s and '80s. He was
the most feared terrorist on the planet.
He was a Venezuelan communist named
Ilich Ramírez Sánchez.
And the media dubbed him Carlos the
Jackal.
And Carlos provided the group with the
weapons that they needed that they
couldn't steal.
I was stationed in Greece from 1998 to
2000. My entire reason for being in
Greece was to infiltrate
and destroy
17 November. We promised Mrs. Welch in
1975 we would find her husband's killers
and we would bring them to justice and
we meant it. It took 27 years. I took
delivery of a level four armored BMW
540.
My next door neighbor was the newly
arrived British Defense Attaché, Steven
Saunders, Brigadier General one star.
I liked Steven a lot.
But he was a media [__] But he was a
media [__] Anytime he saw a camera, he
would run right in front of it and offer
up an interview and he would just loved
being on TV.
We happened to be invited to a cocktail
party
the night of the day that I took
delivery of the new car.
I was standing with Steven, with the
American Defense Attaché, and the French
Defense Attaché. And Steven was making
fun of me because of my new car. As I
said, we lived next door to not next
door, but our backyards abutted. And he
says to me, "You Americans,
you're so paranoid about security." He
said, "This is an EU country. It's a
NATO country. What are you so afraid of?
And everybody starts to chuckle.
And I said to him, "You Brits live in a
dream world if you think that because
they have pretty beaches and palm trees
that they're not going to kill you if
they have the chance. Believe me, if
they have the chance, they're going to
kill you."
And then we all laughed again. To make a
long story short, 2 weeks later, they
killed him. They killed him. They killed
him in broad daylight during a morning
rush. They finally issued a manifesto
several months afterwards in which they
specifically said that they set out that
morning to kill me.
But that I was driving an armored car
and they knew that I was armed. And it
said, "And so we elected to carry out
the revolutionary sentence on the war
criminal Saunders."
That killing, everybody like Steven,
that killing
was what began to change public opinion.
17 November would attack. They killed
the Turkish ambassador, the Turkish
deputy ambassador, they killed the head
of the federal tax office, they killed
the governor of the central bank, they
killed the minister of finance, they
killed the minister of communications,
but they were largely seen as Robin
Hood, right? Oh, taxes were raised? They
set fire to six tax offices and then
murder the head of the tax service.
And people are like, "Oh, okay. Well,
they're for the poor people." No,
they're not for the poor people. It's an
armed criminal gang is all it is. So, in
2002, in April of 2002,
a man was walking in Piraeus with a
paper bag, like a grocery bag,
carrying a bomb. And he was going to put
the bomb underneath the car of a
billionaire shipowner and the bomb went
off. It blew off both of his hands and
blew out his right eye. And as he was
bleeding to death,
a policeman runs across the street,
takes off his own shirt to staunch the
blood squirting out of his stumps, and
the guy confesses to being 17 November's
chief bomber. He names all the members
of 17 November, and he gives the address
of the safe house where all the weapons
are stored.
And then he survived.
And so the Greeks were able to arrest
all of them.
The three
most prominent members received
sentences of 1,765
years in prison.
The only two things that the cops were
never able to recover were the
old-school typewriter that they used to
type the manifestos
and the Webley .45.
It's out there somewhere.
But anyway,
they were unusual in that
the Soviet Union was far too liberal for
them. They were old-school Stalinists.
They wanted you to to fall into line or
face death.
And they saw themselves as the ones to
to carry out that policy.
I want to ask you about Day of the
Jackal because, and this is something
that I've only recently sort of got hip
to,
and that's because there were some
articles written recently that Candace
Owens shared that kind of tied into the
possibility of
French Foreign Legion and this kind of
stuff. I I don't have any theory on
that. I don't
ascribe to all of her theories, but
there was an interesting article written
by a French analyst about the
possibility that there are actual hit
squads, and they might be
considered French, but they might not
actually be French. They might actually
be other uh Middle Eastern countries
that are actually behind some of these
hits.
And I know this is in the French Huh?
They're French. Well, I I doubt that,
but [laughter] but what I'm saying is
that
there might [clears throat] There are
people that theorize that Israel had a
role in the background of some of these
French operations, not just banking, but
also other other things that are going
on in France that not many people are
very hip to. But, I wanted to ask you
about the situation with Day of the
Jackal because that story is about de
Gaulle, and I'm curious So, you're
saying that Carlos the Jackal
is the name came from that? Is that what
you're saying? Yeah, it's a funny thing.
It's one of these chicken or egg
situations where
Carlos was almost caught
in a raid on his friend's apartment in
Brussels. His friend was not a terrorist
and didn't realize that Carlos
that his friend Ilich was Carlos, right?
Although he was not yet known as Carlos.
Anyway, the cops raid the apartment.
Carlos is already gone.
And a French photojournalist took
pictures of like every inch of the
apartment.
And it turned out that the Belgian guy
was reading the book The Day of the
Jackal, and it was on the side table.
The French journalist just decided to
call this unnamed terrorist, we didn't
yet know it was Ilich Ramírez Sánchez,
to call him
the Jackal.
And then it just so happened that a book
that was next to The Day of the Jackal
was written by a Spanish uh I I forget
his name now, but his first name was
Carlos. And so this French reporter just
made it up out of whole cloth, Carlos
the Jackal. And then we we learned later
we learned later that Carlos was like,
"Where the [__] did this name come from?
I don't like this name. Why are they
calling me Carlos? And what's this
Jackal thing? Why are they calling me
the Jackal?" I'll tell you, I met Carlos
in 2000. It took me over a year to get
permission to see him.
He's serving a life without parole
sentence in France for the murder of
seven
French policemen. I had gone to see his
ex-wife, Magdalena Kopp,
in Germany. They They share a daughter.
And she She dropped out of terrorism.
She just She had had enough and she just
dropped out. She had done time in
prison. She was like, "Enough." And she
quit. So, I begged her
to write to Carlos and tell him that I
really did need to talk to him. I wasn't
going to, you know, I'm not trying to
get him in trouble. I only want to know
about the Greeks.
It took over a year. And then of course,
yeah, the the French insisted that they
had to be there. So, I go to Paris. I
meet up with the French. We take a
train.
The prison was like, I don't know, 40
minutes outside of town. And we finally
get into the prison to see Carlos. I
said, "Thank you for seeing me. I'm John
Kyriakou. I'm from the CIA.
We promised Mrs. Welch that we would,
you know, find her husband's killers.
It's been 25 years.
Et cetera, et cetera."
And he listened and he's nodding and
he's nodding. And I said, "All I want to
know is who were the Greeks?
Just give us the names of the Greeks.
Give us one name. Just someone that
would lead me to the killers."
And he goes,
"Fuck you."
And then he just got up and walked away
from the
the you know, one of those Plexiglas
things.
He just got up and walked away. And that
was the end of it. He never gave us
anything.
Two years later, it didn't matter. And
he's still in He's in prison. He'll die
in prison. He's well into his 70s now.
Utterly unrepentant, unapologetic. This
is a guy for for those of your viewers
who who don't know any of the
background. This is a guy
who kidnapped literally every
oil minister from every OPEC country
during an OPEC summit.
There was an OPEC summit taking place in
Vienna, Austria.
He and his gang raided the meeting site
and they kidnapped every member of OPEC
at the same time.
And the Saudis paid him something like a
billion dollars to let everybody go.
It was Carlos that worked with Gaddafi
to set up these training camps in Libya
where the PFLP, the PFLP-GC, the DFLP,
Abu Nidal, the IRA,
Popular Revolutionary Struggle, they all
sent their people there to be trained at
these camps in the desert. Carlos was
the money guy and Carlos was the weapons
guy. Carlos was working with the
Romanians and the Bulgarians. You know,
they were producing gigantic amounts of
weapons and ammunition and just selling
them on the gray market. It was Carlos
that had the relationship with the
Eastern Europeans to buy the AK-47s and
the hand grenades and the land mines and
the bullets and then sell them to these
groups through the Libyans.
It was all very complicated and in my
mind absolutely fascinating. You know,
minus 9/11, I would have spent the rest
of my career just working against these
groups.
I find it fascinating too because again,
it seems rare, at least in my limited
reading and research that this type of a
person is organic or alone, you know,
weapons trafficker or whatever terrorist
person. There there there's usually
networks. There's people behind them.
There's money and power. Is he just out
for his own gain or was he a true
believer in a kind of Leninist
perspective? You know, for him it was a
combination of pure
Marxist ideology and money.
I'm going to tell you one other story
about Carlos.
I've spoken a number of times about a
guy that I used to work with at the
agency. It was a legendary contractor
named Billy Waugh,
w a u g h.
Billy was one short of the US record. He
had 17 Purple Hearts from World War II,
Korea, and Vietnam.
He was a stone-cold
killer. One of these guys that would go
into a village in Vietnam and just mow
down every living thing.
So, he was a long-time CIA contractor.
He and I worked very closely together.
It was actually just the two of us in
the Middle East before 9/11. We did this
long-term operation together.
But, anyway,
he told me the most fascinating story.
The details in a biography about him
that his niece wrote
differ a little, but the core of the
story is the same. The way he told it to
me was was thusly.
He was assigned to the CIA station in
Khartoum, Sudan.
And, you know, it was one of those
situations pre-9/11 where you got to
work 7 days a week. But, every once in a
while, just so you don't go crazy, you
have to take a day off and sleep in.
So, there's one day he and another guy
from the station
go to the vegetable market just to buy
some vegetables.
And
he said he's there buying vegetables and
he looks over
and he sees the only other white man
that he ever saw in Khartoum. And he's
looking at this white guy in the
vegetable market and he says to his
buddy,
"That's Carlos the Jackal."
And his friend says, "Get the [__] out
of here."
He said, "I'm telling you, that's Carlos
the Jackal."
And then Carlos kind of got away in the
crowd. They run back to the station.
Cofer Black, who became the director of
counterterrorism and then later became
ambassador Cofer Black and the chairman
of Blackwater after that. Cofer was the
station chief at the time and Billy says
he ran into Cofer's office. Cofer saw
him on an elliptical machine in the in
the office. And he says, "Cofer, I just
came from the vegetable market and I saw
Carlos the Jackal."
And Cofer says, "Get the [__] out of
here. Carlos the Jackal.
What in the world would Carlos be doing
in Sudan of all places? You're you're
you're nuts."
He said, "I'm telling you it was
Carlos."
So he says, "Well, we can't just cable
headquarters and say Carlos the Jackal's
in Khartoum. We need proof. You got to
get a picture of him."
Billy went back to the vegetable market
every single day for a month.
And then he saw him again.
So what they did is they paid these two
Sudanese guys to get into a fist fight.
And you know,
in Africa and the Middle East, it
fighting is very very rare. So two guys
start duking it out. A big circle forms
around them. Everybody wants to get a
look.
And so that's what happens and Carlos,
kind of a little guy, he runs over to
get a look and he's kind of craning his
neck to see, you know, who's fighting,
what's going on and Billy's there just
going click click click click click
click click click click click click
click click.
They send the film back to headquarters
and they said, "Oh my god, it's Carlos
the Jackal." But he had the presence of
mind after the fight to follow Carlos
discreetly to his house. So they were
able to identify the house.
They initiated an operation where Carlos
was made to be unconscious temporarily.
And when Carlos woke up, he was on a
French military plane
on the way to Paris and he's been in
prison ever since.
These stories are awesome. I love
hearing these kind of stories and
they're not told enough. And again, this
is for the sake of the audience and I'd
like to see what you think about this
now reflecting back to your younger
days.
Why does the US care what
an organization of leftists are doing in
Greece?
Why are you there in Greece? We wouldn't
have cared had they not been murdering
Americans. They killed the CIA station
chief, they killed two US defense
attaches, Bill Nordeen and George
Santis. The bomb that they used to kill
Bill Nordeen was so big
that we found Nordeen's head on the roof
of the next door neighbor's house. They
meant business. They shot and gravely
wounded the US DEA rep in the embassy.
They shot and killed a hapless Air Force
technical sergeant, an African-American
guy named Ron Stewart who was just doing
his laundry. They shot him and killed
him in the laundry room of his apartment
building.
The Greek public hated that too because
he was black. They're like, come on,
this man's oppressed in his own country
and that's the guy that you kill?
So it was because they were actively
targeting Americans
that we went after them like we did.
This may sound like a stupid question,
but my context for this question is not
stupidity.
If I read say Brzezinski or I read
Brzezinski in Between Two Ages, he's got
this footnote where he talks about
Professor Anthony Sutton.
And he quotes Sutton about the build-up
of the Soviet Union. And we find other
references here and there in literature
to certain figures that might have
played or attempted to play both sides
during the Cold War. We think about
Robert Maxwell, we think about an Armand
Hammer, we think about Some people
theorized Lord Victor Rothschild was not
just British intelligence, but might
have also been passing intelligence to
the Soviets. And on the other side,
Nicolae Ceaușescu.
Yeah,
there there seems to be quite a few
instances where
we're fighting this enemy that's also
aided and propped up in many cases and
perhaps the Cold War
according to say Dr. Quigley was a bit
exaggerated, right? In other words, the
memorandum that kicks off the Cold War
that Stalin is building up
is it
exaggerated or is it plausible that the
Cold War is real, but also at a certain
level perhaps desired?
Oh, I think you've hit it on the head. I
think that's exactly what the case was.
Yeah, sure. Historically here in the
United States, Jay, we've always needed
an ism to be opposed to. In the
19-teens, it was anarchism and then it
was communism and then it was socialism
and later on it became Islamism. I mean,
there's always something that we need to
rally against, but at the same time,
that's how
you know, the deep state is able to
justify its budgets.
This isn't anything that's new. It's
been going on for more than a century.
Sure, you have to rally Americans
against something.
You know, it's like Smedley Butler said
a long time ago, war is a racket, right?
Oh, yeah. It would seem to me as well
that World War I and World War II,
although they're obviously tragedies or
serious problems with ideologies.
But again, it's almost like there's a
dialectical
control where you want to have the
opposition to justify the existence. We
just saw this for example this week or
last week, excuse me, with the case that
they're going to put against the SPLC,
you know, sending significant amounts of
money to people heading up these
obviously [clears throat] fake cutout
groups, the ridiculous groups.
>> But also the head of the guy, you know,
the Unite the Right guy at
Charlottesville that I think many of us
thought even at the time this is kind of
a silly kind of honey trap type of
situation. And it would be really
foolish, I think, to be involved in that
kind of stuff and perhaps even similar
situations with J6, although I don't
think that's come up yet in the case of
SPLC, but a similar kind of template of
fomenting, hyping up, causing, funding
the opposition.
In not every case, but in many cases.
And that's why I think, you know, not
many people really talk about this in
regard to the Cold War, that we might
have had very wealthy people in the West
and perhaps banking elites who wanted to
put money into communism, socialism, and
so on, perhaps even fascism, too,
according to Sutton, because, as you
said, it justifies a lot of what we do.
And there's a lot of resource
extraction, there's a lot of
geopolitical tactical, you know, bases
that can be set up. And you exposed, by
the way, maybe I'm not right about this,
but I remember years ago, in the 2000s,
when I was trying to really study all of
this stuff in depth, I remember seeing
all of a sudden
articles popping up, maybe 2008, 9, 10,
11,
CIA black sites exposed. They're in the
news. Suddenly, we've got this place in
Romania, this black site. Right. I think
people probably thought that these
things existed, but then suddenly we
knew that they did exist. And you
called a lot of that out. Yeah. That's
why you got persecuted. Could you
explain, perhaps, to those that are not
familiar with your story,
wh- And I think you're a hero for what
you did. Why
>> Why why call this out? Why are we doing
this? What's the justification from the
establishment's perspective?
Oh, the the justification from the
establishment's perspective was that we
needed to do literally everything to
protect Americans even if what we were
doing
broke the law.
And my position was
we're either going to be a nation of
laws
or we're not.
You we can't be both. You can't You
know, Ronald Reagan called the United
States a shining city on a hill.
A beacon of hope for human rights and
civil rights and civil liberties.
I want that to be true.
And so you can't be that shining city on
a hill
and have a torture program and a secret
prison program and an illegal rendition
program and torture people to death and
then just dig a ditch next to the
torture chamber and dump their body in
the ditch and then talk about how you
support human rights.
So we're going to have to either pick
one or the other.
And I came down on the side of law and
order. I mean I
hate to sound like an ideologue, but I
came down on the side of
you know, the rule of law.
There was a I blew the whistle on the
CIA's torture program in December of
2007.
And I said three things. I said the CIA
was torturing its prisoners, that
torture was official US government
policy, and that the policy had been
personally approved by the president.
And I was prosecuted for that. I wish
that I had blown the whistle on
the secret prison program. There was a
woman
she was a contemporary of mine at the
agency and I I respected her deeply.
She swears that she was not the one who
blew the whistle, so I won't use her
name.
But she was working at the White House
right after right around the time I got
arrested and she was escorted out of the
White House by the Secret Service and
they took her badge and told her never
to come back and then she was forcibly
retired from the CIA.
They said they leaked that she had blown
the whistle on the Well, they didn't say
blow the whistle, that she had leaked
information about the existence of the
secret prisons.
She swore that it wasn't her. And in in
private conversations, she swore to me
that it wasn't her.
And I said, "Well, if it was you, then
you are one of the great heroes of the
early part of the 21st century.
And uh she swore it wasn't her, but
I I don't know. I was just one of those
guys that believed that we were the good
guys. And if we're the good guys, then
we have to act like the good guys. If
you want to be for torture,
you can be for torture, but you have to
change the law. You can't just pretend
that the law doesn't exist or that
because you're the good guy, it doesn't
exist for you,
that nobody else can torture, but you
can.
And so I said, "No, enough is enough."
And I said something.
I've heard you and many others.
And I think it was you. I don't want to
misquote you if it wasn't you, but this
is often said that, you know, when
people say, "What What What is
espionage? What are we doing in all
these other countries?" The answer is
usually given something like "We are
doing illegal activities in other
countries legally."
Or something like that. Yeah. How do you
balance, as you're say
being trained and going into this world,
the idea on the one hand that
there's all these legalities, which
which you mentioned quite often in
interviews. You mentioned, for example,
to Tucker that you know, certain people
in the agency couldn't have public
support for this or that candidate, Bob
Dole or whoever. Right.
>> Uh but at the same time, we've got this
situation where we've got to go in other
countries and do illegal things under
the cover of legality. Mhm. How do you
balance that as you're going through
that and then make the sort of conscious
decision to say, "Well, in this case,
now the torture program is I'm not
defending it. I'm just saying like I'm
curious as to your process as you're
working through these issues."
>> [gasps]
>> You go into a job like that really
believing that you're the good guys.
You really believe it. And you
understand from your very first day that
your job is to break the laws of foreign
countries.
Not to break the laws of the United
States. That is forbidden.
I remember one of my early bosses
telling me,
"Don't ever lie to finance, medical, or
security. They can ruin your life.
Don't ever lie to a judge."
And he said, "And don't ever lie to me.
Everybody else you can lie to.
Everybody's lying all day long. You
know, the the old cliche, how do you
know when a CIA officer is lying? His
lips are moving.
So,
yeah, I I believed that. You know, we go
overseas and we lie, we commit
espionage, we convince other people to
commit espionage or to commit treason
for us because we're the good guys.
But then,
when we're violating the Federal Torture
Act of 1946,
when we're violating the United Nations
Convention Against Torture, which we
which we wrote,
and has the force of law because it was
ratified by the United States Senate,
nobody ever said we could violate the
law in the United States.
You know, if I go overseas, I'm I'm
going to use 1949
as as a an example. If I go overseas and
I receive a cable saying, "Hey, listen,
the polls say that the communists are
going to win the Italian election. So,
steal the election for the
conservatives." I'd say, "Okay."
And then I spend $150,000 recruiting
journalists and and planting stories.
And then, what do you know, the
communists lose.
Well, I I would sleep very well that
night because I'm the good guy and the
communists are the bad guys. And so I
did what my job is. But if the order is
to
overthrow the American government or to
influence an American election or
or
torture someone in violation of American
law?
Absolutely never.
Never.
Because then we're not the good guys
anymore.
Like did we learn nothing over the
course of all these decades? Did we
learn nothing from Watergate, for
example? Nothing from Iran-Contra.
So you got to put your foot down.
You know, you often hear from
establishment types when this topic is
brought up, well, if we don't, they
will. I remember reading
I remember reading decades ago or excuse
me, a book written decades ago. I think
it was John Marks's book about the
Manchurian Candidate and MK Ultra. And
the argument was made at that time, if
we do not engage in these testing
experimentation projects, the Soviets
will. If we don't do this, they will. Do
you find that to be a flimsy
justification and why? Yeah, that's
flimsy. Oh my God, where should we even
start with with MK Ultra and and the sub
the sub operations of MK Ultra, MK
Chickwit and MK what whatever it was
called, Night Rider or whatever it was
called, I can't remember. There were
like six of them.
Imagine
being in a meeting at the CIA and say,
listen, there's this scientist in
Switzerland and he just developed this
thing called LSD
and it does crazy [__]
And we've heard that the Russians are
developing
expertise in mind control and ESP and
what they called remote viewing and all
this silliness that never came to pass.
So we got to do the same thing cuz the
Russians are doing it. In fact, the
Russians weren't doing it. The Chinese
were doing it.
But we didn't have sources in China at
the time.
So
you're in this meeting and a
determination is made that yes, we're
going to do this. We're going to call it
MK Ultra.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to experiment on American
citizens. And we're never going to tell
them we're experimenting on them.
Better yet, let's start by experimenting
on our own employees.
And so, they start dosing their own CIA
employees with LSD. People are jumping
out of windows and off of balconies.
They're like, "Ah, no, we we shouldn't
do it on our own people. Let's just do
it in, let's say, San Francisco."
And then they go to San Francisco. And
they did a whole bunch of horrible
illegal [__] in San Francisco.
Things like
they recruited an army of prostitutes.
And they set up a safe house in San
Francisco. And they said, "Go out and
pick up a date. Bring him back to the
safe house. We're going to dose him with
LSD. And then we're going to see if
he'll give us his most deeply held
secrets
under the LSD."
All it did was it just made people
crazy.
Then they said, "You know what? Maybe we
should do something different. We should
develop a germ.
Let's develop a germ and we'll just
release it into the air and see if it
makes people sick."
So, they developed this this germ.
They waited until an unusually foggy day
in San Francisco.
And then they just drive around town
in these pickup trucks
with pipes releasing the germ into the
fog.
They knew it was successful
when a week later 11 people had gone to
hospital emergency rooms with this
really rare upper respiratory infection.
That we caused.
Then they decided
what it would be like they wanted to
know what it would be like if they could
make like everybody in a town crazy.
And so,
they put LSD
in the flower
that was supplied to the only bakery in
a little village in France.
The hapless baker who had no idea that
the that the flower was full of LSD
made bread that day like he did every
day,
sold the bread to everybody in the
village, everybody in the village went
nuts. There's even a Wikipedia page
about this.
That's the CIA. All of that was illegal.
Now, this was also very, very secret,
top secret until 1975.
The Church Committee on Capitol Hill,
the Church Committee on the Senate side
and the Pike Committee on the House side
developed this information,
and they called the CIA's leadership to
come and testify under oath in public
hearings.
MK Ultra was outed,
and the Director of Central
Intelligence, Dick Helms, Richard Helms,
was specifically told by Senator Church,
"Don't destroy the documents."
He went back to the agency and told
them, "Destroy all the documents."
They destroyed 85% of the documents on
MK Ultra. So, what we know today about
MK Ultra comes from the 15% of the
documents that survived the giant, you
know, destruction.
And that's why we don't have answers to
so many of these questions.
Dick Helms was held in contempt of
Congress. He was fined a few hundred
dollars.
And then when he got back to the agency
after having taken a plea
and having been fined,
there was a parade of CIA employees
standing in the hallway
leading to his office,
each one throwing in cash into a hat to
pay his fine.
They all looked out for each other.
Yeah, it seems like I mean I don't want
to say strictly speaking a cult, but
some people have written about it as if
that's the quote cult of intelligence.
Like that's the Victor Marchetti book.
The idea being then that, you know,
you're sort of bound to almost like a
kind of a quasi secret society perhaps.
Yeah. Maybe that's an exaggeration, but
>> Same idea. Yeah. No, you're right. It's
the same idea. Briefly little detour
here cuz I want to
I've not heard you you probably have
commented I just haven't heard it yet.
You know, lately the government is is
seeming to give a nod at many levels to
so-called aliens and UFOs. I personally
do not believe in aliens, but we do have
a lot of bizarre stories and instances
and and advanced technology that seems
to perhaps mirror or mimic some of these
UFO phenomena. I'm curious of what you
think about that because when I hear
about aliens and UFOs and these stories,
there could be something spiritual going
on for sure, but it also reminds me of
what happens if you have a bad LSD trip.
So Yeah. I and and and we on that topic
of MK Ultra, it makes me wonder if you
know, there couldn't be and I think
there's definitely a you know, a
deep state component to the UFO alien
phenomenon.
But also specifically in the
descriptions of what people go through
and how they describe these experiences,
do you think that there's any likelihood
that this is sort of a propagated
intentional perhaps mythology or idea
that's being seeded or planted that we
are now under some sort of a you know,
alien attack. Maybe you think that the
phenomenon is real. I don't know your
view. Could there be an MK Ultra, I know
it's defunct, but something akin to that
that overlaps with the UFO alien
phenomenon?
Oh, it's absolutely possible. You know,
I I I have to admit I'm of two minds on
this issue.
On the one hand, I long believed that
these sightings that people have are
largely explainable.
And when they're not explainable,
there's I think a likelihood that it's
some kind of experimental technology.
You know, DARPA is working 20 years
ahead of everybody else and
it's probably some top secret, you know,
thing.
On my very first day at the CIA, I had
lunch with my new boss.
And I said, half jokingly, "So, where
are the aliens?"
And he laughed and he said, "That is
the first question that every single one
of us has on his first day."
And I said, "So, what's the answer?"
And he said, "We don't do any of that
stuff. It's all at the Pentagon." He
said, "I have no idea what they are,
where they are. Nobody here does. It's
all at the Pentagon."
With that said,
I've told this story before, but I'll
repeat it.
When I was in high school, my mom and
dad bought a restaurant
in Sharon, Pennsylvania. We lived in New
Castle, Pennsylvania.
So, they're about 15 mi apart. And to go
from New Castle to Sharon, you have to
go through Amish country. And the Amish
don't use electricity. So, it's very,
very dark. One Friday night, my dad and
I left the house because we were working
midnight shift. We always worked
midnight shift on Fridays and Saturdays.
We're driving through Amish country and
there is this brilliant, like blinding
flash of white light. And then there's a
second flash and then a third flash.
And we're both looking up at this thing,
like, "What is that?"
And then this orange trapezoid
lights up and it's just hovering about
1,500 ft off the ground in the shape of,
I hate to say it, in the shape of a
saucer.
And I said, "What is that?" My dad pulls
the car over, we get out of the car,
we're standing there staring at this
thing.
A guy pulls up behind us, gets out of
his car, and he goes, "What is that?"
And my dad said, "I don't know." And
then it goes
at this fantastic speed that just defies
defied
the laws of physics.
Never made any sound.
We stood there for at least another 30
seconds thinking, "Is it going to come
back or what?" I don't know.
So, we get back in the car
and I said to him
mind you, I was 17 at the time, so I
didn't know any better. I said, "So,
should we
like call somebody? Should we call the
cops or something?"
And he said
"And say what?
We saw a flying saucer and it flew
away?"
He said, "People are going to think
we're insane."
And so, the only person I I told was my
mom the next day.
Well, years later, I not years later, a
couple of years later
I come to school here in Washington. I
had a cousin who was an F-15 pilot.
And um I always looked up to him cuz he
was older than me and you know, he's a
pilot and he's so cool.
I said to him
"Hey listen, my dad and I saw this crazy
thing once a couple of years ago." And I
told him.
And he said, "Oh, listen." He said,
"Every one of us at the Air Force
he said, 'We all see [__] like that all
the time. And sometimes they come up out
of the water
off the coast of Norfolk.'"
I said, "What are they?" He said, "I
don't know." He said, "But they very
well could be ours.
It's just that he said, 'I'm not cleared
to know what it is. I don't know what
the heck it is.'" I said, "Well, what do
you do when you see something like
that?" He said, "We fill out a form. We
send it to the Pentagon and nobody ever
hears about it again.
So, I I don't know. I I I've never seen,
you know, little green men or anything
like that. I I
I I wonder, too, if, on the one hand,
I I lean in the direction of some kind
of futuristic advanced technology,
right? That's being experimented with.
On the other hand, I wonder
if
let's say it is something
extraterrestrial,
the government all these years hasn't
wanted to panic us.
Okay, well, guess what? Now, all this
video has been leaked from the Pentagon
over the last 5 years and nobody cares
and there hasn't been any panic. So, why
not just come out with it now and tell
us what it is?
I feel very similarly about that topic.
I do want to shift gears a little bit
because there's so many hot topics I do
want your take on. A lot of them are,
unfortunately, I know this is selfish,
but kind of my pet thoughts. That's why
I want to bounce my my theories and my
thoughts off of you. Gordon Thomas wrote
a fascinating book about Mossad called
Gideon's Spies many years ago. He's a
journalist and there's several chapters
that related to the Vatican and the Cold
War. Particularly, the chapter on John
Paul II was interesting because
there were significant advancements that
Israel was able to achieve in terms of
recognition and influence through John
Paul II on record. I don't think that's
any anything too controversial.
>> Right. He discussed, for example, the
Vatican becoming hip to the Mossad
wanting to and trying to bug the
Vatican. Then, I noticed, if you look at
the dates, not too long after that, John
Paul II did recognize the nation-state
of Israel as a political entity, which
the Vatican had not done for many
decades. And that to me is a window into
the possibility of a back door
connection or influence there that might
be pretty significant geopolitically
speaking because you do have the Roman
Catholic Church taking some pretty
significant advances in terms of
changing their attitudes towards
the nation state of Israel and
forbidding Judaism in the last several
decades post Vatican II. I'm curious
to what degree do you think that is a
window into a influence campaign? Is it
significant? Do you think that's
plausible? And there also seems to be
significant admissions in that book and
other books as well with related to
Gladio that the CIA had a really close
connection, perhaps even more than a
connection, perhaps
people on the hook to what the CIA
wanted throughout the Cold War in
regards to the Vatican.
Yeah.
>> Was that a trap to basically sort of
have soft power influence through the
Vatican? Yeah.
That was always my understanding. Yes.
There were old-timers at the agency when
I first joined who took credit for
making John Paul the second Pope.
That's what I've heard, yeah. Yeah, this
was a political decision from the very
beginning.
It was done to weaken the Soviet Union.
They knew that having a Pope from
Poland, which was a Soviet satellite
state at the time, would reap untold
benefits because it would distract the
Soviets. And then at exactly the same
time, the Solidarity movement took root
in the beginning in the Gdansk shipyard
in Poland. And so there was no downside
for the West to John Paul being Pope. If
anything, this was like a gift.
And the recognition of Israel, I
remember how controversial that was at
the time. That was just like an extra
added freebie
that we got on top of everything that we
got with the Soviets.
So yeah, I think that was the case.
I remember, you know, a lot of the texts
will point to, you know, a pretty close
relationship with Henry Kissinger Yes.
>> even going back to Paul the VI having a
very close relationship there as well as
William Casey. I think you know, that
you had this period where there were
pretty hardcore traditional Catholic
people in the CIA like Casey and others
known as Templars
that were very committed to that
alliance and I suspect and I wonder I
know that
has opposed Trump in recent months
and then there was this meeting where
Cardinal Christoph back in January was
at the White House and there was these
tense words supposedly said and there's
this story that they reminded Cardinal
Christoph and Leo of the Avignon papacy
and the power that the state can have
and I'm just to me I just thought that
was a fascinating window into perhaps
what's going on with
not just the deep state but the deep
church and perhaps an influence in in
that structure.
And you know there was a book published
recently in the last I'm going to say
year or two and I I apologize that I
don't remember the title
talking about the joint CIA Vatican
operation to publish Doctor Zhivago
and to Where did you say this? Yeah, I
didn't even know this. I heard you say
this. Yeah, make it available to Soviet
citizens at the International Book Fair
in Brussels in like 1971
one or whatever whatever it was where
you had even the KGB minders
who had accompanied this delegation of
Soviet citizens to the International
Book Fair themselves were bringing
copies of Doctor Zhivago back to the
Soviet Union. It's funny it was a book
that that nobody really paid any
attention to until the Cold War got
really hot and then somebody at the CIA
said we've got to smuggle this into the
Soviet Union or how do you do that?
Well, we can do it by asking the Vatican
to do it for us.
You know, so the Russians were all over
the American book tent at the
International Book Fair not paying any
attention at all to the Vatican book
tent and every time a Soviet citizen
would come to the Vatican tent they'd
say hey you want to go in the back room
there's a back room. You're going to
want to go back there." And then they
had all these copies of Doctor Zhivago
in Russian.
It got to the point where people would
would tear out like 10 pages at a time
and just tape them around their legs
and then just, you know,
re-enter the Soviet Union with the book
taped around their legs 10 pages at a
time,
collate the pages again,
and then pass it around to their
friends.
I think I have an idea as to why. And
for those that don't know, I did write a
book and two other books after that,
Esoteric Hollywood, which largely deals
with propaganda in films and in
Hollywood and in fiction. But for those
that might not know in the audience, and
you've talked about this in many
interviews, John, which is the interest
that the CIA and other entities,
Pentagon even, military, they have in
Hollywood and fiction,
why would the the CIA care about Doctor
Zhivago? What What is that going to do
in the Soviet Union? Who cares about
that? Why would they do that?
Yeah,
it's it's funny. You declare victory in
small increments,
right? And so, if you are able to get a
book like Doctor Zhivago into the hands
of a Soviet citizen
and maybe make one Soviet citizen
question his or her own government,
that's a successful operation.
You plan small and hope for the best.
And that's really what it was all about.
There's a movie I know you're very
familiar with, Three Days of the Condor.
Yeah, it's And you've got Robert Redford
sitting in this, you know, bookstore and
he's basically just reading books and
looking for things all day long.
Is that real or is that exaggerated?
No, that that's real.
That's real. When When I first joined
the agency, that was called active
measures.
Yeah, it it's it's all about the
propaganda and it's all about combating
propaganda. It's a 24-hour a day, 7-day
a week process. In films, something like
The Americans and we see back during the
Cold War, number stations are putting
out the message codes to the Soviet
operatives in the US. If I recall, it's
been some years since I watched Three
Days of the Condor, but Robert Redford's
like scanning for propaganda, but isn't
it also perhaps like messages from
Soviet operatives to certain cells or
something like he's trying to see if he
can find something Maybe it's not, I
don't remember. Does that still go on in
terms of I know there's number stations
sort of putting out those codes and
whatnot.
Is that still happening at that type of
a level? Okay.
Oh, yeah. As recently as a week ago, I
was just
I just did a podcast episode of my own
where I talked to two former CIA
colleagues. One was a CIA attorney and
the other was a anti-Soviet operations
officer. And we were talking about that
and I said, "You know,
when I was 9 years old
I've said this before. When I was 9
years old, I told my parents I wanted to
be a spy when I grew up.
And they bought me walkie-talkies and
disappearing ink and stuff like that for
Christmas. When I was 16, I told them I
wanted to be a spy in the Middle East.
And I I meant it and I became a spy in
the Middle East. Well, my dad, when I
was 9, my dad took me to an auction at
one of these local farms. We lived in a
very rural area.
And at the end of the auction, all the
junk that didn't sell, they just threw
into one box and my dad got the box for
50 cents. And it included a shortwave
radio.
So, that night
we put some batteries in this thing and
I listened to an AM station. It was WGN
in Chicago. And I remember thinking,
"Wow, I'm in Newcastle, Pennsylvania and
I can hear a station in Chicago." Cuz
you know, when the sun goes down AM
stations go on augmented power and if
you're a 50,000 W station, you can be
picked up
as much as like 1,500 mi away. So, I was
getting Chicago and New York and Boston
and Atlanta and Dallas a couple a couple
times.
The next night, I switched it to
shortwave just to see if I can get this
this on AM, what about this shortwave?
And I got BBC and Radio Moscow and Radio
Havana and all different kinds of of
things. Well, one of the things that I
heard that night and many many nights
after that
was just a man's voice
saying
eight
three
six for hours. And I'm like, what is
this? What what it is, it's a spy
what he's doing is called reading from a
one-time pad. So, he's reading an
encrypted message by giving only the
numbers associated with the letters
that are encrypted.
So, those numbers will change with every
message. So, I mentioned this on the
podcast the other day, and the the other
case officer, he said, "Oh, listen." He
said, "I still listen to shortwave, and
I can tell you that a week ago
I heard a guy reciting one-time pad
numbers."
So, there it's some Russian spy
somewhere in the United States and he's
reading it from his one-time pad.
There was a number station down in Miami
that's like near Cuba that's still
spitting out numbers codes. And I know
for the British have these as well. Um,
so I'll go ahead and start reading the
super chats. HushTone says, "Jay, you
look like clavicular, you're
Jay-vicular." Good one. Albert Smith,
$5. Jay, you've got another sad hair
day. Well, I didn't want to look too
silly
uh talking to John Kiriakou, so I just
went with I don't know, Rob Thomas from
Matchbox 20 mixed with James Bond. So,
Ralph says $10. Jay, you're researching
topics but you're muted. Okay, we
unmuted. Reckon $5. Bro, in case you
didn't know you're live. I know. Jay Mel
$15.
Why are so many XCIA in US politics? And
what about the Democratic Party say
Governor Virginia? Can we trust any of
these people, John?
No.
We can't trust them.
>> Easy answer.
>> [laughter]
I I I'll tell you
I was I was a mentor to a guy, Will
Hurd. Will is an was an awesome case
officer, as honest as the day is long.
Our politics were different but I I
loved the guy.
And um he told us one day he said,
"Listen, I'm going to resign." I was
like, "What?" I said, "Will, you're a
natural born case officer. Why would you
resign?" He says, "I want to run for
Congress."
I said, "Run for Congress, buddy." I
said, "That's that's not a step up.
It's not."
Well, he he resigned and he ran for
Congress and he won. Here's a guy who's
half black, half white and he wins three
times in a Supreme Court mandated
majority Hispanic district.
That's how honest and popular he was.
And then he decided it's all posturing,
no real work gets done. I'm going to
quit and run for president. He runs for
president for about 15 minutes a year
two years ago.
He dropped out before the primaries even
began and the last I heard he was on the
board of directors at OpenAI making
millions and millions and millions of
dollars. So, it worked out for him. But,
you know, people like Elissa Slotkin and
and Abigail Spanberger, it's all about
the power. Listen, Abby, even at the
agency Abby
Abby was known as somebody who wasn't
going to be around long because she
needed she needed time to win election
to different offices so that she could
run for president. That's what it's all
about. Elissa Slotkin's exactly the same
way.
The idea is that automatically they're
both attractive candidates for vice
president.
And then the next time when it's their
turn,
they run for president. It's all about
power. That leads me to the last
question I had for you on my list here
as we kind of wind down with the super
chats.
And that is we cover quite a bit on my
channel, the idea of
high-level steering committees,
foundations, NGOs, think tanks. They
seem to have a lot of power.
Yeah. Americans look at the president,
they look at the, you know, Congress,
they look at the the Senate, you know,
Supreme Court. And certainly those
entities have power, but it seems like
the
there's certain agendas that never
change with the politicians that come
and go. For example, our foreign policy
seems to be dictated by Israel for many,
many decades. Yes.
>> Um what is the real
level of power, you could say, for these
types of supra-governmental
entities, these steering committees,
CFR, Trilateral, or AIPAC, you know, as
a lobby group, or perhaps beyond that,
something beyond AIPAC, a mega group,
something like that. What's the real
power structure, John?
Oh, they're all part of what we are now
calling the deep state, all of them.
CFR is a great example.
Bilderberg is another. I I um
Someone to whom I was once very close,
I'll put it that way,
found herself in a position where she
began attending these meetings.
And I said, "You got to tell me what
what goes on in these meetings? What are
they talking about? Are they like,
you know, manipulating global markets
and, you know, foreign policies and
stuff?" And she said, "It's all about
weapon sales.
All of these meetings, whether it's
Shangri-La or Bilderberg or any of them,
it's all about weapon sales. Yes, the
Bill Clintons and the Bill Gates of the
world and and the, you know,
prime ministers of this country and that
country, they're all talking about the
big overarching global issues and
economies and stuff like that. Yes, but
at the end of the day, it all comes down
to which defense contractor made what
deal.
At every one of these conferences. Well,
that would also still overlap with tech
because we we heard this
>> Absolutely.
>> We we heard this last Bilderberg meeting
on a couple weeks ago. What dominated
the supposed talking points were CBDCs,
AI, and seems like Bilderberg the last
10 years has has really allegedly
focused on a whole lot of tech stuff. Is
that Is that fit in with that?
Absolutely, yes. Right now, it's all
about tech and I think it will be even
more so in the in the future. Yeah, it's
all about tech. Container $15 J, what
does John, and he did mention this
earlier, what does John think about SRI
and CIA programs studying remote
viewing?
For the CIA, remote viewing was a
failure. They could never figure it out.
They could never make it work. It was
always my understanding the Russians
also failed.
The Chinese failed. I think it's just
not possible. I think it's not a thing.
Hush says for $10 John, could you tell
us what you think about Elpidophoros?
There was a discussion of a phone call.
I can't remember the original video.
What did you think of that?
Uh see, now you're going to put me on
the spot here.
>> Maybe. I don't
You know, if you if you want to don't
want to say, you don't have to say.
Elpidophoros is the archbishop of the
Greek Orthodox Church in America.
He is widely believed
to be
by far the leading candidate to be the
next ecumenical patriarch of
Constantinople.
He's young. He's 58 years old. He's
good-looking.
He's widely respected.
He has not been kind to me personally.
Maybe I should leave it at that.
Fair enough. Hendrix says, Olaf Palma of
the Swedish Prime Minister He's a
Swedish Prime Minister in the 1980s. Was
assassinated. Was a Yeah, assassinated
probably by a Gladio cell.
There was a a CIA operation called Red
Socks where they had tiny mustache men
followers in the Ukraine. And this was
part of the Maidan coup. Interesting, I
had not heard that. But he's saying that
there's a cell that is similar to that
group that was He's saying is a Gladio
cell that in the Ukraine was called Red
Socks, which helped with the Maidan coup
is what he's saying. Huh.
I have no idea. I always heard that
Palma was killed by a Kurd.
He ended up being convicted and then and
then
on appeal the conviction was overturned.
He was released and they never
conclusively solved that murder.
Mountain Walk, $10. Jay, ask John does
he glow in the dark? Well, he's a
whistleblower, so if that's what you're
referring to.
This is not a formal announcement yet,
but we are winding down my deep focus
podcast and we're going to start a new
in 2 weeks
on YouTube under Real John Kiriakou.
It's going to be called John Kiriakou's
briefing room.
That'd be a different channel or the
same channel redone?
It's going to have to be a different
channel, I'm sorry to say. Okay. And
Jay, when you came on my show, we went
for an hour and a half talking about
mostly about Orthodox theology and
threats to to Orthodoxy. It was
fascinating. I couldn't believe 90
minutes had passed and and they turned
it into three separate episodes. It was
wonderful.
>> Perfect. Yeah, that's great. And that is
going to be on the deep focus or is it
going to be on your new channel? Where
is that going
>> That's going to be on the new channel.
Okay, awesome. Let's see. Porphyry says
there's a secret Asian peptide. Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> It starts with really weird questions
though. Here come all the schizos. I'm
joking.
Uh Jude says for $5, to clarify my last
question, I want to know can John talk
about what was going on in his time in
the Middle East? That's a broad
question.
Lots was going on in the Middle East. On
the one hand, you had the Arab-Israeli
peace process, which we believed at the
time was really taking hold. When I was
stationed in Bahrain, we actually
sponsored the Arab-Israeli peace talks
on the environment. And then I went to
Oman for the Arab-Israeli peace talks on
water.
I mean, it was weird to see like Israeli
flags flying in Bahrain and Israeli
diplomats walking around. Crazy. At the
same time though,
the first intifada began while I was in
Bahrain and got pretty ugly, like really
ugly. I mean, people died, others were
executed. It was nasty. I I went into
Kuwait City with the Marines on
Liberation Day back in '91 and then, you
know, 9/11 and
it was kind of crazy. Josh says, "Thank
you both. John, have you noticed any
patterns from CIA or FBI drawing from uh
recruiting Mormons or perhaps or other
cult groups like Quakers, Jehovah's
Witnesses, or Scientologists?"
Oh, yeah, yeah. I never encountered a
Scientologist, but Mormons are very,
very overly represented in both the CIA
and the FBI, to a very slightly lesser
extent in NSA. And the reason is simple.
Number one, they've never done anything.
They don't swear, they don't drink, they
don't smoke, they don't gamble, they
don't screw around, they don't do
anything. They don't even eat chocolate.
And so they just blow right through the
polygraph exam.
More importantly,
is most of them go on these missions
when they're 18 or 19 years old, and
they go to Brigham Young to the mission
center, and they learn how to speak
these funky languages that nobody else
speaks. Uzbek, Tajik, Pashtu, these
African languages. And so they arrive on
the job already fluent in these
languages, and they can be sent
operationally immediately overseas. So
the agency and the bureau just love
Mormons.
Yeah, absolutely. By the way, that's a
vindication of something that people
will keep challenging me on when I
mention that. Jude says for $10, what I
was specifically asking John about with
the Middle East earlier. I'm sorry, I
couldn't find your other super chat. You
said, "What did John think was going on,
for example, in the Antiochian Church
during his time in the Middle East?"
I attended the Antiochian Church when I
was stationed in the Middle East just
because there was no Greek Orthodox
Church.
Specifically in Kuwait, the Antiochians
were very strong.
You know, I don't remember there being
any controversy when I was living there
in the '90s.
It was all pretty straightforward. And
then when I was stationed in Bahrain, I
was very close friends with the Greek
Consul General.
She was a Greek American.
There was no Cypriot representation
there, so she covered Cyprus as well.
And then she said to me one day, "Hey,
Archbishop Christodoulos is going to
come to Bahrain, and he wants to meet
with the Emir. We're going to have all
of the Orthodox, the Greeks and the
Cypriots,
go with him to see the Emir." The Emir
was surprised to see me. He had no idea.
I mean, there was no reason why he would
have known that I was Orthodox.
We had the meeting, and then he pulls me
aside,
and he says to me, he whispers,
"I like your Ayatollah." He He "I like
your Imam. I trust him." And I said, "He
likes you, Your Highness." Next thing
you know, the Emir donates a giant plot
of land. It was like 2 acres.
And we built the first ever Orthodox
church in Bahrain. It was very very
generous. In Kuwait, there were already
Orthodox churches. Later on, toward the
end of the '90s, they built an
Antiochian church in Doha.
I was in Dubai a few weeks ago.
And there are churches in both Dubai and
Abu Dhabi.
I don't think there's anything in
Muscat, and absolutely absolutely
positively nothing in Saudi Arabia
anywhere. You'll lose your head.
Um, but things were going pretty well
for the Antiochians when I was living
there.
Henrik says, "Have you guys read Which
Path to Persia from 2009 Brookings
Institute?" Yes, I've I've read the
whole thing. I'm familiar with it. I did
actually look it up the other day. In
it, they admit that the US will go to
war for Israel and Iran. The US is not
getting bombed by Iran, but the Gulf
allies are. And I assume John probably
agrees with that. Yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely.
John, are there other members of N17
that perhaps never got caught and
continue in Greek leftist parties?
Yes.
There was one in particular who admitted
that he was one of the two shooters in
the Welch assassination. He dropped out
of 17 November. He was the only one to
voluntarily leave and join the Greek
Communist Party and became the president
of Greece's largest labor union.
Greece is one of those rare countries
which very stupidly has
a statute of limitations on murder.
And so, he was never prosecuted. He got
away scot-free with the Welch
assassination. Banana says for $20,
"John, can you talk about the CIA
culture and its influence on America,
for example, in universities, Middle
Eastern countries, and spreading
Americanism in terms of soft power.
Wow. We we would need a whole episode
for that.
The answer obviously is you're exactly
right. That CIA soft power is being
exerted everywhere that you've just
cited, whether it's in television
series, or Hollywood movies, or the
media, or across universities. You know,
I was recruited by my grad school
professor, and then with passage of the
1993 Equal Employment Opportunity Act,
that became illegal. So, what they did
is they just went around the EEOC. What
they do now is if you are within 3 years
of retirement and you're a senior
operations officer,
they'll send you back to your alma mater
to teach some innocuous course. A buddy
of mine right now is teaching a course
at Indiana University called
Espionage in Soviet Literature.
Nobody gives a [__] about Espionage in
Soviet Literature. The whole point of
the class is for people to come up to
him after class and say, "Hey, I'd
really like to join the CIA." And then
he says, "Let me introduce you to a
friend of mine."
That's what it's for. This is from Penny
for $20. Is House of Cards worth
watching, or what are the TV shows or
movies that really give insights into
accuracy with the CIA?
House of Cards definitely is worth
watching. That is the story of the
Clinton family.
I mean, they don't even try to mask it.
House of Cards is about the Clintons.
Yes.
Don't miss it. But an even better show
is The Americans. A former colleague of
mine in the CIA's Counterterrorism
Center, Joe Weisberg,
resigned.
I remember the day he resigned, he he
came up to me, he said, "Buddy, I just
resigned." I was like, "What? Why would
you resign?" And he said, "This job is
just not for me." He said, "I don't have
it in my gut to convince somebody to
commit
treason." He said, "I I can't do it."
But he was unmarried, no kids. I said,
"What are you going to do?" He said,
"I'm going to go to Hollywood and find
my fortune."
And he he published a very highly
regarded novel that was heavily redacted
because it was so true to life. And then
immediately created The Americans. And
never has to work again a day in his
life.
Yeah, it's great show. It's my favorite
one of my favorite TV shows, definitely.
We we've done several podcasts with our
good buddy Mark Hackard, Russia analyst,
specialist, translator. Translates KGB
stuff. And of course he did a great
podcast with me on The Americans.
Everybody be sure and follow John
Kiriakou. John, thank you so much. I'm
honored to speak with you and so so
proud of your work and what you're doing
and seeing you all over all these
podcasts. And great episode on Tucker,
by the way.
Thank you very, very much. I appreciate
it. It's good to see you again.